start doing jobs, we don't have to do them anymore, and we get freed up from drudgery and toil. Now, when I talk about this with my friends in Cambridge and Silicon Valley, they say, "Fantastic. No more drudgery, no more toil. This gives us the chance to imagine an entirely different kind of society, a society where the creators and the discoverers and the performers and the innovators come together with their patrons and their financiers to talk about issues, entertain, enlighten, provoke each other." It's a society really, that looks a lot like the TED Conference. And there's actually a huge amount of truth here. We are seeing an amazing flourishing taking place. In a world where it is just about as easy to generate an object as it is to print a document, we have amazing new possibilities. The people who used to be craftsmen and hobbyists are now makers, and they're responsible for massive amounts of innovation. And artists who were formerly constrained can now do things that were never, ever possible for them before. So this is a time of great flourishing, and the more I look around, the more convinced I become that this quote, from the physicist Freeman Dyson, is not hyperbole at all. This is just a plain statement of the facts. We are in the middle of an astonishing period. ["Technology is a gift of God. After the gift of life it is perhaps the greatest of God's gifts. It is the mother of civilizations, of arts and of sciences." — Freeman Dyson] Which brings up another great question: What could possibly go wrong in this new machine age? Right? Great, hang up, flourish, go home. We're going to face two really thorny sets of challenges as we head deeper into the future that we're creating. The first are economic, and they're really nicely summarized in an apocryphal story about a back-and-forth between Henry Ford II and Walter Reuther, who was the head of the auto workers union. They were touring one of the new modern factories, and Ford playfully turns to Reuther and says, "Hey Walter, how are you going to get these robots to pay union dues?" And Reuther shoots back, "Hey Henry, how are you going to get them to buy cars?" Reuther's problem in that anecdote is that it is tough to offer your labor to an economy that's full of machines, and we see this very clearly in the statistics. If you look over the past couple decades at the returns to capital -- in other words, corporate profits -- we see them going up, and we see that they're now at an all-time high. If we look at the returns to labor, in other words total wages paid out in the economy, we see them at an all-time low and heading very quickly in the opposite direction. So this is clearly bad news for Reuther. It looks like it might be great news for Ford, but it's actually not. If you want to sell huge volumes of somewhat expensive goods to people, you really want a large, stable, prosperous middle class. We have had one of those in America for just about the entire postwar period. But the middle class is clearly under huge threat right now. We all know a lot of the statistics, but just to repeat one of them, median income in America has actually gone down over the past 15 years, and we're in danger of getting trapped in some vicious cycle where inequality and polarization continue to go up over time. The societal challenges that come along with that kind of inequality deserve some attention. There are a set of societal challenges that I'm actually not that worried about, and they're captured by images like this. This is not the kind of societal problem that I am concerned about. There is no shortage of dystopian visions about what happens when our machines become self-aware, and they decide to rise up and coordinate attacks against us. I'm going to start worrying about those the day my computer becomes aware of my printer. (Laughter) (Applause) So this is not the set of challenges we really need to worry about. To tell you the kinds of societal challenges that are going to come up in the new machine age, I want to tell a story about two stereotypical American workers. And to make them really stereotypical, let's make them both white guys. And the first one is a college-educated professional, creative type, manager, engineer, doctor, lawyer, that kind of worker. We're going to call him "Ted." He's at the top of the American middle class. His counterpart is not college-educated and works as a laborer, works as a clerk, does low-level white collar or blue collar work in the economy. We're going to call that guy "Bill." And if you go back about 50 years, Bill and Ted were leading remarkably similar lives. For example, in 1960 they were both very likely to have full-time jobs, working at least 40 hours a week. But as the social researcher Charles Murray has documented, as we started to automate the economy, and 1960 is just about when computers started to be used by businesses, as we started to progressively inject technology and automation and digital stuff into the economy, the fortunes of Bill and Ted diverged a lot. Over this time frame, Ted has continued to hold a full-time job. Bill hasn't. In many cases, Bill has left the economy entirely, and Ted very rarely has. Over time, Ted's marriage has stayed quite happy. Bill's hasn't. And Ted's kids have grown up in a two-parent home, while Bill's absolutely have not over time. Other ways that Bill is dropping out of society? He's decreased his voting in presidential elections, and he's started to go to prison a lot more often. So I cannot tell a happy story about these social trends, and they don't show any signs of reversing themselves. They're also true no matter which ethnic group or demographic group we look at, and they're actually getting so severe that they're in danger of overwhelming even the amazing progress we made with the Civil Rights Movement. And what my friends in Silicon Valley and Cambridge are overlooking is that they're Ted. They're living these amazingly busy, productive lives, and they've got all the benefits to show from that, while Bill is leading a very different life. They're actually both proof of how right Voltaire was when he talked about the benefits of work, and the fact that it saves us from not one but three great evils. ["Work saves a man from three great evils: boredom, vice and need." — Voltaire] So with these challenges, what do we do about them? The economic playbook is surprisingly clear, surprisingly straightforward, in the short term especially. The robots are not going to take all of our jobs in the next year or two, so the classic Econ 101 playbook is going to work just fine: Encourage entrepreneurship, double down on infrastructure, and make sure we're turning out people from our educational system with the appropriate skills. But over the longer term, if we are moving into an economy that's heavy on technology and light on labor, and we are, then we have to consider some more radical interventions, for example, something like a guaranteed minimum income. Now, that's probably making some folk in this room uncomfortable, because that idea is associated with the extreme left wing and with fairly radical schemes for redistributing wealth. I did a little bit of research on this notion, and it might calm some folk down to know that the idea of a net guaranteed minimum income has been championed by those frothing-at-the-mouth socialists Friedrich Hayek, Richard Nixon and Milton Friedman. And if you find yourself worried that something like a guaranteed income is going to stifle our drive to succeed and make us kind of complacent, you might be interested to know that social mobility, one of the things we really pride ourselves on in the United States, is now lower than it is in the northern European countries that have these very generous social safety nets. So the economic playbook is actually pretty straightforward. The societal one is a lot more challenging. I don't know what the playbook is for getting Bill to engage and stay engaged throughout life. I do know that education is a huge part of it. I witnessed this firsthand. I was a Montessori kid for the first few years of my education, and what that education taught me is that the world is an interesting place and my job is to go explore it. The school stopped in third grade, so then I entered the public school system, and it felt like I had been sent to the Gulag. With the benefit of hindsight, I now know the job was to prepare me for life as a clerk or a laborer, but at the time it felt like the job was to kind of bore me into some submission with what was going on around me. We have to do better than this. We cannot keep turning out Bills. So we see some green shoots that things are getting better. We see technology deeply impacting education and engaging people, from our youngest learners up to our oldest ones. We see very prominent business voices telling us we need to rethink some of the things that we've been holding dear for a while. And we see very serious and sustained and data-driven efforts to understand how to intervene in some of the most troubled communities that we have. So the green shoots are out there. I don't want to pretend for a minute that what we have is going to be enough. We're facing very tough challenges. To give just one example, there are about five million Americans who have been unemployed for at least six months. We're not going to fix things for them by sending them back to Montessori. And my biggest worry is that we're creating a world where we're going to have glittering technologies embedded in kind of a shabby society and supported by an economy that generates inequality instead of opportunity. But I actually don't think that's what we're going to do. I think we're going to do something a lot better for one very straightforward reason: The facts are getting out there. The realities of this new machine age and the change in the economy are becoming more widely known. If we wanted to accelerate that process, we could do things like have our best economists and policymakers play "Jeopardy!" against Watson. We could send Congress on an autonomous car road trip. And if we do enough of these kinds of things, the awareness is going to sink in that things are going to be different. And then we're off to the races, because I don't believe for a second that we have forgotten how to solve tough challenges or that we have become too apathetic or hard-hearted to even try. I started my talk with quotes from wordsmiths who were separated by an ocean and a century. Let me end it with words from politicians who were similarly distant. Winston Churchill came to my home of MIT in 1949, and he said, "If we are to bring the broad masses of the people in every land to the table of abundance, it can only be by the tireless improvement of all of our means of technical production." Abraham Lincoln realized there was one other ingredient. He said, "I am a firm believer in the people. If given the truth, they can be depended upon to meet any national crisis. The great point is to give them the plain facts." So the optimistic note, great point that I want to leave you with is that the plain facts of the machine age are becoming clear, and I have every confidence that we're going to use them to chart a good course into the challenging, abundant economy that we're creating. Thank you very much. (Applause)
empiecen a hacer nuestro trabajo, nosotros ya no tendremos que hacerlo más, y seremos liberados del trabajo arduo y monotono. Cuando hablo de esto con mis amigos en Cambridge y en el Valle de Silicio, me dicen, "Fantástico. No más monotonía ni trabajos fatigantes. Esto nos da la oportunidad para imaginar un tipo de sociedad totalmente diferente, una sociedad donde las reuniones de creadores e iventores, de diseñadores y realizadores, con sus jefes y patrocinadores sean para conversar, recrearse, compartir ideas, y provocarse mutuamente". Es, en verdad, una sociedad que se parece bastante a las conferencias TED. Y hay mucho de verdad en todo esto. Estamos presenciando un increíible florecimiento. En un mundo donde hacer un objeto es tan fácil como imprimir un documento, tenemos nuevas y fantásticas posibilidades. Quienes solían ser iniciados y artesanos ahora son creadores y son responsables de gran cantidad de innovación. Y los artistas, que estaban limitados, pueden ahora hacer cosas que antes no podían. Asi que este es un tiempo de gran florecimiento, y mientras más veo a mi alrededor, más me convenzo que la frase del físico Freeman Dyson no es para nada un hipérbole. Es simplemente una declaración de los hechos. Estamos a la mitad de un periodo sorprendente. [" La tecnología es un regalo de Dios, que después del regalo de la vida, es quizá su más grande regalo, madre de civilizaciones, del arte y la ciencia".] Lo cual nos plantea otra gran pregunta: ¿Qué podría salir mal en esta nueva era de la máquina? ¿Nada? ¡Fantástico... no se diga más... prosperemos... vámonos a casa! Vamos a enfrentar dos conjuntos de desafíos realmente espinosos a medida que nos adentremos en el futuro que estamos creando. El primero es económico y está realmente bien resumido en una historia apócrifa de un cruce de sátiras entre Henry Ford II y Walter Reuther, quien era el jefe del sindicato de trabajadores automotrices. Estaban recorriendo una de las nuevas fábricas modernas y Ford, bromeando, mira a Reuther y le dice, "Oye Walter, ¿cómo harás para que esos robots paguen las cuotas sindicales?" Y Reuther replica, "¿cómo harás tú Henry, para que compren autos?" —Risas— El problema de Reuther en esa anécdota es que es dificil ofrecer la fuerza de trabajo en una economía que está llena de máquinas, y lo vemos claramente en las estadísticas. Si se mira los retornos sobre capital de las dos últimas décadas, —en otras palabras, las ganancias empresariales— vemos que suben, y que están hoy en el punto más alto de todos los tiempos. Si miramos los rendimientos en mano de obra, en otras palabras el total de los salarios pagados en la economía, los vemos en su punto más bajo y alejándose rápidamente en la dirección opuesta. Así que estas eran claramente malas noticias para Reuther. Parece que estas fueran excelentes noticias para Ford, pero realmente no lo son. Si quieres vender grandes cantidades de bienes más bien caros a las personas, querrías entonces contar con una clase media grande, estable y próspera. Hemos tenido una así en Estados Unidos durante casi todo el periodo de la posguerra. Pero la clase media está claramente bajo una gran amenaza hoy en día. Todos conocemos bien las estadísticas, pero permítanme recordar una de ellas, el ingreso promedio en EE UU ha bajado en estos últimos 15 años, y estamos en peligro de quedar atrapados en un círculo vicioso en el que la desigualdad y la polarización continúan creciendo con el tiempo. Los desafios sociales que vienen con ese tipo de desigualdad merecen cierta atención. Hay un conjunto de desafíos sociales que en realidad no me preocupan tanto, y que son capturados por imágenes como estas. Este no es el tipo de problema social que me preocupa. Que no haya disminución de las visiones distópicas sobre lo que pasará cuando nuestras máquinas se vuelvan auto conscientes y decidan levantarse y coordinar ataques contra nosotros, es algo de lo que me empezaré a preocupar el día en que mi computadora adquiera conciencia de mi impresora. (Risas) (Aplausos) Así que esos no son los desafíos por los que debemos preocuparnos. Para precisar los tipos de desafios sociales que surgirán con la nueva era de la máquina, quiero contarles una historia sobre dos trabajadores estadounidenses estereotipo. Y para que sean realmente estereotipos, hagamos que ambos sean unos tipos blancos. El primero es un profesional educado en la universidad, del tipo creativo... gerente, ingeniero, doctor, abogado, ese tipo de trabajador. Vamos a llamarlo "Ted". Está en la cima de la clase media estadounidense. Su contraparte no fue educado en la universidad y trabaja como obrero; trabaja como dependiente. Hace trabajos de oficina o manuales de bajo nivel en la economía. Vamos a llamar a esa persona "Bill". Si retrocedemos unos 50 años, hallaremos a Bill y a Ted llevando vidas bastante similares. En 1960, ellos, por ejemplo, muy probablemente tenían empleos de tiempo completo trabajando por lo menos 40 horas a la semana. Pero tal y como lo ha documentado el investigador social Charles Murray, desde que empezamos a automatizar la economía, y en 1960 las computadoras recién empiezan a ser utilizadas en los negocios, desde que empezamos a inyectar progresivamente la tecnología, la automatización y las cosas digitales en la economía, las vidas de Bill y Ted cambiaron significativamente. Durante este periodo, Ted ha conservado su trabajo de tiempo completo. Bill no. En muchos casos, los Bill han salido por completo de la economía, mientras que los Ted lo han hecho solo en raros casos. Al paso del tiempo, Ted ha disfrutado de un feliz matrimonio, Bill no. Y los hijos de Ted han crecido en un hogar de dos padres, mientras que los de Bill no. ¿De qué otras formas los Bill están desapareciendo de nuestra sociedad? Sus votos en las elecciones presidenciales han disminuido y han empezado a ir a prision de forma más frecuente. Asi que no puedo contar una historia feliz sobre estas tendencias sociales y no se ve ningun indicio de que se revertirán. Son ciertas independientemente del grupo étnico o demográfico que miremos, y se están volviendo tan severas que existe el riesgo de que opaquen incluso los increíbles avances que logramos con el Movimiento de los Derechos Civiles. Y lo que mis amigos del Valle del Silicio y de Cambridge están pasando por alto es que ellos son Ted. Ellos estan viviendo estas vidas increíblemente ocupadas y productivas y tienen todos los beneficios para probarlo, mientras que Bill lleva una vida bastante diferente. Ambos son prueba de lo acertado que estaba Voltaire cuando hablaba sobre los beneficios del trabajo, y del hecho de que este nos salva no de uno, si no de 3 grandes males. ["El trabajo salva al hombre de tres grandes males: el aburrimiento, el vicio y la necesidad". - Voltaire] Asi que, ¿qué hacemos con estos desafíos? El manual de economía es sorprendentemente claro, sorprendentemente directo, especialmente a corto plazo. Los robots no se quedarán con todos nuestros trabajos el próximo año o el siguiente, así que el manual básico de economía nos servirá: Fomentar el espíritu empresarial, reducir a la mitad la infraestructura, y asegurarnos de que estamos sacando a las personas de nuestro sistema educativo con las habilidades apropiadas. Pero a largo plazo, si nos estamos moviendo hacia una economía que esta llena de tecnología pero baja en trabajo, y lo estamos haciendo, entonces tenemos que considerar algunas intervenciones más radicales. Por ejemplo, algo como un ingreso mínimo garantizado. Esto probablemente incomode a algunas personas en este recinto, porque esta idea está asociada con la extrema izquierda y con esquemas bastante radicales para la distribución de las riquezas. He hecho un poco de investigación al respecto, y tal vez tranquilice a algunos saber que la idea de un ingreso mínimo neto garantizado ha sido defendida por rabiosos socialistas como Friedrich Hayeck, Richard Nixon y Milton Friedman. Y si les preocupa que algo como el ingreso garantizado vaya a sofocar nuestra motivación por el éxito y nos vuelva algo complacientes, tal vez esten interesados en saber que la movilización social, una de las cosas de las que realmente nos enorgullecemos en los Estados Unidos, es ahora menor que en los países al norte de Europa, que tienen redes de seguridad social bastante generosas. El manual económico, entonces, es en verdad bastante preciso; el social es bastante más desafiante. No sé cuál es el manual para hacer que Bill se emplee y se mantenga empleado durante su vida. Lo que sí se es que la educacíon es una gran parte de ese proceso. Soy testigo de primera mano de eso. Fui un niño Montessori durante los primeros años de mi educación, y lo que esa educación me enseñó es que el mundo es un lugar interesante y que mi trabajo es salir a explorarlo. El colegio se acabó cuando estaba en tercer grado, y entonces entré al sistema de educación pública, y se sentía como si hubiera sido enviado al gulag. Con el beneficio de la retrospectiva, ahora sé que trataban de prepararme para la vida como dependiente o obrero, pero al mismo tiempo sentí que trataban como de aburrirme y de que cayera en una sumisión con lo que sucedía a mi alrededor. Tenemos que hacerlo mejor que esto. No podemos seguir terminando como Bills. Vemos algunos retoños de cosas que mejoran. Vemos a la tecnología impactando profundamente en la educación y empleando personas, desde nuestros más jovenes aprendices hasta los más viejos. Vemos voces de negocios bastante prominentes diciéndonos que necesitamos replantear algunas de las cosas que hemos estado estimado por mucho tiempo. Y vemos esfuerzos bastante serios y sostenidos, e informados, por entender cómo intervenir en algunas de las comunidades con más problemas que tenemos. Entonces, los retoños estan ahí. No pretendo que se entienda que lo que tenemos es suficiente. Estamos frente a desafíos bastante difíciles. Para dar solo un ejemplo, hay cerca de 5 millones de estadounidenses que han estado desempleados por al menos 6 meses. No vamos a arreglar las cosas para ellos mandándolos de regreso a Montesssori. Mi mayor preocupación es que estemos creando un mundo donde tengamos tecnologías deslumbrantes incrustradas en una especie de sociedad desgastada y respaldada por una economía que genera desigualdad en lugar de oportunidad. Pero en realidad no creo que hagamos eso. Creo que haremos algo mucho mejor por una muy simple razón: Los hechos estan siendo expuestos. Las realidades de esta nueva era de la máquina y el cambio en la economía están siendo ampliamente conocidos. Si quisieramos acelerar el proceso, podríamos hacer cosas como hacer que nuestros mejores economistas y políticos jueguen "¡Jeopardy!" contra Watson. Podríamos mandar al Congreso de viaje en un carro autónomo. Y si hacemos suficientes cosas de este tipo, se terminará por entender que las cosas van a ser diferentes. Y entonces estaremos listos para la pelea, porque no creo ni por un segundo que hayamos olvidado cómo resolver los desafíos dificiles o que nos hayamos vuelto tan apáticos o duros de corazón como para no intentarlo. Empecé mi charla con frases de oradores que estaban separados por un océano y un siglo, déjenme terminarla con palabras de políticos que estaban igualmente distantes. Winston Churchill fue a mi casa del MIT en 1949, y dijo, "Si vamos a llevar al grueso de las personas de todas las latitudes a la mesa de la abundancia, esto será solo mediante mejoras incansables de todos nuestros medios de producción técnica". Abraham Lincoln se percató de que había otro ingrediente. Dijo, " Soy un firme creyente en las personas. Si se les dice la verdad, se podrá contar con ellas para enfrentar cualquier crisis nacional. El secreto está en darles los hechos escuetos". Asi que la nota optimista, el gran secreto con el que quiero dejarlos es que los hechos tajantes de la nueva era de la máquina se estan volviendo claros, y que confío plenamente en que los usaremos para trazar un buen curso para la desafiante, y abundante economía que estamos creando. Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)